So today's דף *daf* is ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed Amud Bet*. We're
in the middle of a very important discussion of the principle of
זקן ואינו לפי כבודו zaken ve'eino lefi kevodo. *zakein ve'eino lefi kevodo*,
of limits to what you do not have to return the אבידה
aveidah? *aveida*. And based on the very top of ל' עמוד ב'
*Lamed Amud Bet*, although today's דף *daf* is... oh yeah, thanks. What?
He's coming up? Alright, I'll mention it in a minute. We're going
to... today I should mention that today is the יארצייט *yahrtzeit* of...
I'm
sorry...
Henny Gutman, חנוך בן חיים יוסף *Chanoch ben Chaim Yosef*, son of
our dear member Joe Gutman. And the learning should be in his
memory and his memory should be for a blessing.
So we continue on ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed Amud Bet* and three
lines from the top. And we're discussing this principle that there are
times you don't return an object. What if it violates a מצווה
mitzvah *mitzvah* like you'll have to go into a cemetery, which the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says should be obvious. But also if it is...
if it's going to mean greater loss to you than gain to
the person to whom you're returning it.
And that's based on a principle of a very important ethical principle
of Judaism
that your sort of, your primary person that you're responsible to is
yourself. Which again doesn't mean that you put your desires above other
people's needs, but it means that your needs are of greater precedence
than somebody else's needs. And therefore you have to first protect your
own property before you protect somebody else's. So you didn't need a
special פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of והתעלמת מהם *ve'hitalamta mehem*. So the third,
so what we do learn out from the verse והתעלמת מהם *ve'hitalamta
mehem*, which we read not rhetorically but as a statement that sometimes
you are allowed to not return an object, is when it is
beneath your dignity. That it's not protecting your,
your sort of your property before somebody else's property, but protecting your
dignity over somebody's property. And that's the principle of כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot? *kavod habriot*. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* actually discusses at some length
when there's a significant affront to dignity, when there's a significant issue
about shame that would come to somebody, a person's body, a dead
body in the street. Or תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* also talks about going
naked, that those types of things could even sometimes allow you to
forgo even ritual obligations. And but certainly even at a lesser degree,
it can allow you to forgo financial
responsibilities, responsibilities towards somebody else's property. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, two lines
from the top on ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed Amud Bet*. אמר רבא
Amar Rava *Amar Rava*, so רבא Rava *Rava* says, הכישה חייב chayev
בה ba *hishicha chayav bah*. Although you... if it's beneath your dignity
you don't have to return an object, let's say it's a sheep,
to go ahead and pick up a sheep and carry it through
town and ask whose sheep is this. But if you sort of
engaged it, you started returning it, then you can't now disengage. If
you hit it, you have to now return it. Now this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* would sound like it would be true in general. Like
I have a right to pass by the אבידה aveidah? *aveida*, but
as soon as I stop to pick up the אבידה aveidah. *aveida*,
I become obligated and then I cannot claim my exemption anymore. But
another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that this is not generally true. This
is specifically about livestock, because once you pick up livestock then it
is going to sort of follow you and you cannot restore it
to its previous state. You can't just put it back there and
now somebody else will find it or whatever. Now it's going to
be sort of following after you or you've caused it to stray
even further. So that's why you become particularly obligated by livestock. But
if there was somebody's wallet there and it was beneath my dignity
to return it and I picked it up, at least according to
another גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it's not clear here, I could say, wait
a minute, this is going to mean me schlepping through town, it's
not going to be appropriate for me or whatever, and then I
could just put it back where I found it. So that's not
clear from this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does
clarify that. Let's see what this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. אביי הוה
יתיב קמיה דרבא *Abaye hava yasiv kamei de'Rava*. אביי *Abaye* was sitting
in front of רבא Rava *Rava*. חזא להני עיזי דקיימי *Chaza le'hanei
izzi de'kaymi*. He saw that there were some goats
standing there and presumably they were wandering a little bit lost. שקל
קלא ושדא בהו *Shakal kala veshada behu*. He took a clump of
dirt and he threw it at them
to maybe push them away. But it doesn't sound like that. It
sounds like he was trying to somehow, I don't know, lead them
and maybe take care of them. אמר ליה amar lei, *Amar lei*,
so רבא Rava, *Rava* said to him, איחייבת בהו *ichayavtes behu*. Now
you're obligated to take care of them, to make sure they get
returned. Okay, איחייבת בהו קום אהדרינהו *ichayavtes behu kum ahadrinhu*. Go return
them. This by the way fits into what I just said, because
it doesn't sound like אביי *Abaye* was trying to return it. But
once he was starting to engage it, even if he was trying
to just shoo them away, but now he became responsible because now
his actions have led to them maybe straying further and now he
has to make sure that they are going to get back to
their right master. איבעיא להו *Ibaya la'u*. Now we ask the question.
דרכו להחזיר בשדה besadeh ואין דרכו להחזיר בעיר ve’ein darcho lehachazir be’ir
*Darko le'hachzir basadeh ve'ein darko le'hachzir ba'ir*. How does a person determine
whether it's beneath his dignity or not? Let's say if here's an
object that I find out in the field and for me to
like, go
to, out in the field where it's not everybody's around, all the
people whom I'm it's important for me to sort of hold myself
in a particular way, it's out there
in the country, so there would be okay for me to ask
a few people, hey, do you know whose sheep this is? But
once... But for for me to go looking around in the city
and trying to return a sheep, that would be beneath my dignity.
Okay, and apparently the point though so that’s the question and I
found it in the field, okay, but it might be that I
won’t find anybody in the country whose sheep it is and then
I’ll have to bring it to the city and start asking around
in the city. Okay, so but in the current context it is
within my dignity. But it might lead up to me having to
go bring it into the city and it would be beneath my
dignity. מה? What do we say? מי אמרינן השבה מעליא בעינן Mi
amrinan hashavah ma’alya be’inan
that in the end you have to do a full returning, your
obligation to return incorporates all possibilities. וכיון דלאו דרכיה לאהדורי בעיר לא
מחייב Vecheivan delav darchyei le’ahadurei be’ir lo mechayev
and since it won’t be within your dignity or you know normal
for you to look and to return it in the city, therefore
ואין דרכו להחזיר בעיר what was it? לא מחייב lo mechayev
so I’m not obligated because part of the returning it incorporates things
that are beneath my dignity. או דילמא O dilma
or do we say בשדה מיהא הא איחייב ליה Besadeh miha ha
ichayev lei since I became חייב in returning it here out in
the field and in this context it’s within my dignity וכיון דאיחייב
ליה בשדה vecheivan de’ichayev lei besadeh so therefore I start being obligated
and once my obligation kicks in even if I can’t even if
it now means that I’m going to have to bring it into
town איחייב ליה בעיר ichayev lei be’ir now I’m gonna also be
obligated, you know now I do become fully obligated and then I
have to see it through and even work to return it in
the city. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו Teiku we don’t know.
Yes.
I’m just trying to understand, I mean as far as I understood
the obligation of הכרזה hachrazah you go to the אבן הטוען Even
HaToen three times every רגל regel right?
Yeah, it’s a good question. I had always understood that what it
meant that it’s not לפי כבודו lefi kevodo meant that it’s not
לפי כבודו lefi kevodo for me to like stoop down and pick
it up. But that’s not that does not sound at all this
way from the גמרא Gemara and an earlier רש״י Rashi says where
was the earlier רש״י? Rashi? רש״י Rashi says
where was the רש״י? Rashi?
And there was an earlier רש״י Rashi that says that it’s not
לפי כבודו lefi kevodo oh שישיבנה sheyeshivennah
meaning it’s not that the picking it up is not לפי כבודו
lefi kevodo but the act of returning, right? So but yeah I
mean the point is so you’re I mean so yeah but we
don’t we saw before the אבן הטוען Even HaToen was a specific
thing during the רגלים regalim during the time of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash or whatever. Otherwise it means going around to the שולס,
shuls, going around to the בתי מדרש. Batei Midrash. So it’s not
just a one-time putting a posting in the newspaper. Whatever the context
requires. Yeah fine but whatever the context requires look I don’t even
believe even in the time of the משנה Mishnah everybody just waited
till the רגל. regel. It would have been a הפקר וועלט hefker
velt I assume there was a more immediate way you tried to
return it immediately locally to the people who would have lost it.
Okay, you know if you found it out in your little city
in נהרדעא Nehardea you didn’t wait three months for the רגל regel
to announce it in בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
It makes no sense so you know what’s בשדה right near your
עיר? ir? Does he actually have to go then again and...
Yeah because the animal out in the שדה sadeh are owned by
the people in the עיר. ir. Alright anyway so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר רבא amar Rava: said רבא Rava, כל שבשלו
מחזיר בשל חבירו נמי
מחזיר. Kol she-bishelo machazir be-shel chaveiro nami machazir. Here’s a good way
of determining whether it’s לפי כבודו. lefi kevodo. Would you bother doing
this if it were your own object? Now that works if it’s
like if it’s a question about stooping down and picking it up.
If I drop you know some pennies in the middle of Times
Square I’m not going to stoop down and pick them up. I’m
going to let it lay there. Okay so I wouldn’t do it
with my own object I’m not going to do it with somebody
else’s. It’s a little bit different though in terms of the act
of returning. If the act of returning means going around and knocking
on doors and asking somebody you know how do you measure that
in terms of your own object? I guess you ask yourself if
this was what would be required of me to get me back
my own object would I go around and knock on doors? Let’s
say I would reverse it. Would I go and knock on doors
and ask people if they had found my object or something? Although
it is a little different so I’m not exactly sure how you
do this thought experiment but רבא Rava is trying to help you
determine whether you’re honestly you know whether you’re shirking your obligations or
you it’s an honestly לפי כבודו. lefi kevodo. Ask yourself would you
do it for yourself? Yes.
Is dignity at all related to the wealth of the person? Just
like I’m a wealthy person my stooping down to do this thing
but the person who lost it would really like it back right?
But that’s part of what לפי כבודו lefi kevodo is. That’s what
the point is. Right, right, if it’s not if it’s beneath me
me you know here I am although it is funny because like
for me given you know you know if I’m this millionaire for
me to pick up to stoop down and pick up a nickel
is not לפי כבודו lefi kevodo but to be returning a nickel
for a or somebody who lost it for whom it matters, that
might be- that might be appropriate לפי כבודו, l'fi k'vodo, right? So
you mean- you mean the context is not just that I'm willing
to forgo it, it's that the context of am I doing it
for myself or doing it for others impacts whether it's consistent with
my dignity or not. Which is an excellent point, which is why
Rava's sort of thought question of would you do it for yourself
is not always the best way to determine. Absolutely, it's an excellent
point. Okay. והכל שבשלו פורק וטוען ובשל חברו אינו פורק וטוען. v'hakol
shebishlo porek v'toen uv'shel chaveiro eino porek v'toen. We're going to see,
we're going to very soon deal with another mitzvah which is similar
to the mitzvah of השבת אבידה, hashavat aveidah, of unloading and reloading
somebody's donkey that's collapsing under its weight. And similarly there, if it's
not according to your dignity you don't have to do it. How
would you determine if it's not fitting for your dignity as opposed
to you just being lazy? Well, ask yourself would you do it
yourself if it were your own animal. And again, as David points
out, there could be different things that factor in and make that
a different reality of whether it's consistent with your dignity, but at
least that's a thought question to start trying to assess it. Okay.
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי הוה קאזיל באורחא. Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi hava
ka'azil b'orcha. Rabbi Yishmael son of Rabbi Yosi was going in the
way. פגע בההוא גברא. paga b'hahu gavra. He saw a certain man.
הוה דרי פתכא דאופי. hava dari pitcha d'ufi. He was carrying like
a bundle of sticks, I guess. Yes, a bundle of sticks. אותבינהו,
atvinehu, so he put them down וקא מיתפח v'ka mitpach and he
was like taking a breather. אמר ליה, amar lei, so then he
said to him, דלי לי, dali li, you know, help me back
with this, load it back on me. Interesting question: is that the
mitzvah of טעינה? te'ina? It's not your donkey, it's yourself. Okay, but
either way, he was asking him to give him some assistance in
a monetary matter, in a matter related to his property, so it's
in this broad category of like השבת אבידה hashavat aveidah and פריקה
וטעינה prika u'te'ina which you're allowed to forgo if it's not appropriate
to your honor. Here I am, I'm this like noble person, I'm
going to start like you know dealing with these dirty sticks? So
he didn't want to do it. So אמר ליה, amar lei he
said to him, כמה שווין? kama shavyan? How much is it worth?
אמר ליה amar lei, פלגא דזוזא, palga d'zuza, a half of a
zuz, you know, five bucks. יהיב ליה פלגא דזוזא, yahiv lei palga
d'zuza, so he said, 'I'll buy it from you.' He gave him
five bucks, a half of a zuz. ואפקרה. v'afkera. Now he didn't
want a bundle of sticks. So after he bought the bundle of
sticks he said, 'Okay, they're hefker now.' הדר זכה בהו, hadar zacha
behu, so the guy said, 'Great!' so he took it back. He
could go- oh, he says, 'I could go on like this all
day!' הדר יהיב ליה פלגא דזוזא, hadar yahiv lei palga d'zuza, so
then he said, 'Now help me load them back up.' He said,
'No, no, no, I'll buy it from you. Here's another half of
a zuz.' ואפקרה v'afkera and he was mafkir it. חזייה דהוה קא
בעי למזכי בהו הדר, chazayei d'hava ka ba'ei l'mizkei behu hadar, he
saw the guy wanted to take it yet again. Okay? So he's
like, you know, 'This is a good business!' So אמר ליה, Amar
lei so then Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi said, 'No. לכולי עלמא אפקרינהו,
l'chulei alma afkrinehu, for everybody else they're hefker, לך לא אפקרינהו, lach
lo afkrinehu, for you they're not hefker. Let somebody else take them.'
Okay. Now ומי הוי הפקר כי האי גוונא? u'mi havei hefker ki
hai gavna? Does that even work? והתנן, v'hatnan, we taught in the
mishna, בית שמאי אומרים הפקר לעניים הפקר. Beis Shammai omrim hefker l'aniyim
hefker. If you make something hefker just for poor people, it works.
ובית הלל אומרים אינו הפקר עד שיפקיר לעניים ולעשירים כשמיטה. u'Beis Hillel
omrim eino hefker ad sheyifkir l'aniyim u'l'ashirim k'shmita. No, no, no. Something
is only hefker if it's open to anybody to take, like shmita,
both for rich and poor. You cannot make something selectively hefker. So
how would such a thing even work? אלא רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
לכולי עלמא אפקרינהו. ela Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi l'chulei alma afkrinehu. It's
true. He really did make it hefker to the whole world including
this guy. ובמילתא בעלמא הוא דאוקמיה. uv'milta b'alma hu d'ukmeih. And he
was just pushing him off. He was just, you know, it wasn't-
technically the guy could have been zocheh again, but he was telling
him, 'No, no, no, you're not allowed to be zocheh,' because he
didn't want to go on like this all day. He wanted to
not have to help this guy with his thing, but also not
deprive the guy of his parnassa. So therefore he said, 'I'm mafkir
it to everybody except you.' Okay. Now the Gemara says like this:
והא רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי זקן ואינו לפי כבודו הוה. v'ha Rabbi
Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi zaken v'eino l'fi k'vodo hava. Why do you have
to buy it? Why couldn't he just say, 'I'm sorry buddy, I
can't help you. Ask the next guy. This is not within my
dignity.' Gemara says: No, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי לפנים משורת הדין הוא
דעבד. Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi lifnim mishurat hadin hu d'avad. And an
idea that we've seen come up a number of times in Bava
Metzia, particularly in this perek, he was doing beyond the letter of
the law. דתני רב יוסף, d'tani Rav Yosef, Rav Yosef taught: והודעת
להם, v'hodata lahem, זה בית חייהם. zeh beis chayeihem. You should teach
them: this is the way of their life. This is by Yisro.
I think it's very fascinating, right? When Yisro gives this advice to
Moshe and he gives it before Matan Torah, והודעת להם את הדרך
ילכו בה ואת המעשה אשר יעשון. v'hodata lahem es haderech yelchu vah
v'es hama'aseh asher ya'asun. Chazal understand that Yisro is telling Moshe: don't
just teach them halacha, don't just teach them mitzvos. There's a way
in which they have to live their lives that goes beyond technical
like mitzvos and halacha. And it's very interesting like he's getting this
advice from a non-Jew before Matan Torah. You know, so it's almost
like this sort of like larger wisdom or reality about living, learning
about living one's life that's not completely sort of you know reduced
or defined completely by just the technical mitzvos. So what does that
include? So- so first is זה בית חייהם. zeh beis chayeihem. Now
in one place Rashi says בית חייהם beis chayeihem means like learning
Torah. But again from the context it doesn't sound that way and
here Rashi says בית חייהם beis chayeihem means getting a parnassa. You
know, you should teach them a way that they have to make
their way in the world, teach them, you know, it's not just
about halacha. They have to learn to get a parnassa. את הדרך,
es haderech, זו גמילות חסדים, zo g'milus chasadim, the way that they
go is gemilus chasadim, like it's a way you live your life
even again not To, you know, not just the the the the
halakhic mandate suggestions. Well, I don't know, the מהרש"א Maharsha has a
דרשה drasha about that. ילכו yelchu that to walk זה ביקור חולים
ze bikkur cholim is visiting the sick, the גמרא Gemara will discuss
what that means in contrast to גמילות חסדים. gemilut chasadim. בה that
they walk in it זו קבורה zu k'vurah burying the dead, again
another form of גמילות חסדים. gemilut chasadim. ואת המעשה ve'et hama'aseh the
act, that's the actual what the law mandates. אשר יעשון asher ya'asun
that they should do, that they should strive to doing is maybe
the point. זו לפנים משורת הדין zu lifnim mishurat hadin going beyond
the letter of the law. Okay, so there's the law that they
must do and that's what they should be doing אשר יעשון, asher
ya'asun, the ideal what they should be striving to. Okay. So there
are sort of general ways in which you live your life I
would say just out of like מענטשלעכקייט, mentshlekhkeyt, גמילות חסדים, gemilut chasadim,
you know, being kind to people, having a, getting a פרנסה, parnassa,
right ways to live your life in general. Within the context of
the law itself, there's the law and the spirit of the law.
Okay. So there's like a broader morality that's not even about the
spirit of the law and then there's the law and then there's
the spirit of morality לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin what you
should be striving to. Okay. And that's why he did this because
even though he wasn't required, it was the right thing to do,
you know, within the spirit of the law. תוספות Tosafot says, you
know, there's a תוספות at a few places discusses how come sometimes
the גמרא Gemara, sort of speaks about this and weights it on
this פסוק pasuk of לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, other times
the גמרא Gemara quotes a פסוק pasuk. of למען תלך בדרך טובים,
lema'an telech bederech tovim, you know, says speaks an idea of doing
the right thing but doesn't use the context of within the the
דרשה drasha and saying the spirit of the law. And one answer
תוספות gives is because here really everybody else would have been mandated
to return it. You had a special exemption. So the idea of
לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin here is really saying like you
should not be taking every exemption that you're entitled to. Okay, you
should be doing the right thing, the sort of the general law
that applies, you know, for everyone even though it is true technically
speaking you're allowed an exemption here. So that's like one aspect of
לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. Don't just claim every exemption that
you are able to claim. Okay, but there's other times where actually
no, even for everybody you're not required to do this but the
right thing is to still do it anyway. Okay, so there's different
types of ways of conceptualizing לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. Anyway,
that's why he did it. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to
דרשן darshan this פסוק. pasuk. Let's take a look. אמר מר: amar
mar: ילכו זה ביקור חולים yelchu ze bikkur cholim that they should
go is visiting the sick. היינו גמילות חסדים hainu gemilut chasadim but
that's in that's just a form of doing like, you know, kind
deeds to other people. So concern with other people's welfare. Why specifically
identify ביקור חולים? bikkur cholim? So the גמרא Gemara, says: לא נצרכא
אלא לבן גילו. lo nitzrecha ela le'ben gilo. Okay, this is an
idea we said before about בן גילו ben gilo which is sort
of like somebody born under the same constellation, somebody who is like,
you know, your, you know, your מזל mazal is sort of linked
to to some degree. So why is that relevant? דאמר מר: de'amar
mar: בן גילו נוטל אחד מששים בחליו ben gilo notel echad mishishim
be'chalyo that if you go ahead and you visit somebody who is
your בן גילו, ben gilo, who's in your same like I said,
you know, group, let's just call it that way, then you actually,
you help him, you same something like your same astrological sign, I
don't know if it's exactly that. Anyway, so so you help him
because you remove some of his sickness, one sixtieth. But it's because
you take it. You get a little bit of his sickness. So
you might think that you're not obligated to do ביקור חולים bikkur
cholim to somebody if you're actually gonna get a little sick yourself.
Okay. ואפילו הכי מיבעי ליה למיזל לגביה ve'afilu hachi mibayei lei lemizal
legabeih even so you should go and visit him. Okay, which is
an interesting point. Like, you know, people say I don't want to
go do ביקור חולים bikkur cholim because I don't like visiting hospitals,
you know, let's say I'm afraid of catching of getting sick. Now
by the way obviously you have to take care of yourself, we
just learned before that your primary moral responsibility is to yourself. If
there's really a reason to be afraid of infection or whatever, you
know, or you're just a person that it is, so obviously you
don't, you know, you that has to come before you do an
act of ביקור חולים, bikkur cholim, especially now you can just make
a phone call or something, not that that's the thing. Anyway, but
within the גמרא's Gemara. context where there wasn't a real risk, it
was just like you get a little bit of his sickness, this
idea of one sixtieth, that nevertheless you still would be obligated to.
Okay. בה זו קבורה ba zu k'vurah and you also have to
go ahead take care of burial of the dead. יטול ממנו? yitol
mimenu? Yeah, but you really you take it.
Exactly, which is why you would think you'd be exempt. Okay. בה
זו קבורה ba zu k'vurah and you also have to go ahead
take care of burial of the dead. היינו גמילות חסדים hainu gemilut
chasadim isn't that another form of doing acts of, you know, take
care of other people's well-being? No. לא נצרכא אלא לזקן ואינו לפי
כבודו. lo nitzrecha ela le'zaken ve'eino lefi kevodo. Back to our זקן
ואינו לפי כבודו. lefi kevodo? It's beneath their dignity, which is again
very funny, right? Because if you think that within a religious society
and a context which praises the ideas of returning lost objects, burying
the dead, and so on, why is it אינו לפי כבודו? eino
lefi kevodo? It's like you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah, you know. So
but it's so anyway the גמרא Gemara though recognizes that it still
might be possible. You know, like in a very different context the
גמרא Gemara in כתובות Ketubot speaks talks about a person who would
dance at a wedding and he would like go crazy in terms
of his dancing, this big rabbi, right? And he sort of said,
you know, sort of like דוד המלך David Hamelech who would go
crazy dancing before the ארון, aron, right? Who should determine what is
לפי כבודו? lefi kevodo, We might be sort of saying from a
religious perspective you're doing a מצוה mitzvah that should be לפי כבודו,
you know, who cares about what other people's perspective. Okay, and here
though the point is that opposite of what we said before is
that here you're supposed to bury the dead even though it's אינו
לפי כבודו. eino l'fi kvodo. All right, now is that
because the idea of the dead is also an issue of כבוד
הבריות? kevod habriyot So it's that person's כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot, versus
your כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyot. right? It's not like that person's money
versus your כבוד הבריות. kevod habriyot It's the כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot
of the dead person, of the dignity of the body, you know?
So it's interesting questions, is this sort of saying that this is
a strict obligation even if it's אינו לפי כבודו eino l'fi kvodo
because it's again that כבוד הבריות outweighs yours, or is this more
of the like לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin type of an
idea?
Okay, you'll notice if
you just look at the little letters that point to where this
is quoted in הלכה, halacha, that there's a little letter that brings
down the הלכה halacha of visiting the sick even if you get
a little sick yourself, even if it's like this בן גילו ben
gilo scenario, okay? But there's nothing that brings down the הלכה halacha
about burying the dead if it's אינו לפי כבודו. eino l'fi kvodo.
All right? So it's interesting to think how does this factor into
what we discussed before, is this דין din or is this לפנים
משורת הדין? lifnim mishurat hadin? Now the גמרא Gemara. goes on, okay.
השם Hashem buried משה. Moshe. Yeah, exactly. השם Hashem buried משה, Moshe,
right, exactly, exactly. Maybe the whole point is that we shouldn't even
acknowledge that this could be considered אינו לפי כבודו. eino l'fi kvodo.
Like by money we're willing to acknowledge it, right? But maybe this
we won't don't even want to even acknowledge that you have a
right to think of it as אינו לפי כבודו. eino l'fi kvodo.
It's interesting. Okay. I mean from legislating on Torah obligation to go
outside of Torah obligations, which is לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin
to begin with. Right. Exactly. Well, right. Okay, that's always a good
structure of the question about that. Okay, אשר יעשון זו לפנים משורת
הדין. asher ya'asun zu lifnim mishurat hadin. ואמר רבי יוחנן לא חרבה
ירושלים אלא שדנו בה דין תורה. v'amar Rabi Yochanan lo charva Yerushalayim
ela she-danu bah din Torah. ירושלים Yerushalayim was only destroyed because they
judged the דין din of the תורה. Torah. אלא דיני דמגיסתא לדינו?
ela dinei d'magista l'daynu? So what should they do? They should make
a judge of some like of some unjust society? What do you
mean? It was bad that they applied תורה Torah law? No, אלא
אימא שהעמידו דיניהם על דין תורה. ela eima she-he'emidu dineihem al din
Torah. They were, it was destroyed because they they were exacting that
everything was just about דין. din. ולא עבדו לפנים משורת הדין. v'lo
avdu lifnim mishurat hadin. I did my religious obligation, I did my
הלכה halacha obligation, I'm done. Okay, dope, that's what the הלכה halacha
says, end of story. Right? There was never any broader discussion of
what the right thing is to do, or the spirit of the
law, it was all just about the law. And that's what ultimately
led to the destruction of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, interesting, how does that
tie into the idea of destroying ירושלים? Yerushalayim? So anyway, I would
say take a look at, I'm going to be writing about it
in my פרשה parsha sheet this week, so you can either look
at my פרשה parsha sheet or look at the introduction of the
נצי"ב Netziv to ספר בראשית. Sefer Bereishit. He actually deals with this,
some of these ideas of לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin and
this version of this אגדתא aggadata about לא חרבה ירושלים. lo charva
Yerushalayim. Okay, let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. Next משנה.
Mishnah. איזו היא אבידה? eizo hi aveidah? What's an example of an
אבידה? aveidah It's like hello, what have we been dealing with until
now? But the גמרא Gemara. will ask that question, yes. Does do
we see majority of times לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin appear
is it with regards to גמילות חסדים gemilut chasadim or is it
more? לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin is an interesting question, like
at least off the top of my head, the vast majority of
applications of לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin in the גמרא, Gemara
if not all of them, are sort of interpersonal and דיני ממונות
dinei mamonot types of obligations, right? If I were to sort of
say like, oh, I'm going to be extra careful on שבת Shabbat
and even though I know I'm allowed to do whatever, I'm not
going to do it because I want my שבת Shabbat to be
an extra, you know, even more holy and even more קדוש, kadosh,
we wouldn't call that, you know, it normally wouldn't be called לפנים
משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. It would be called something else, you
know what I mean? לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin tends to
be about being מחמיר machmir or being מקפיד makpid on שבתות, Shabbatot,
קדושת שבת. kedushat Shabbat. לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin is often
very much about my interpersonal obligations. All right, but so you're right,
to say broadly it means spirit of the law is a little
imprecise, right? I don't know if that's what you were asking, but.
No. Grabby there. Okay, got it. All right, let's take a look
at the next משנה. Mishnah. איזו היא אבידה? eizo hi aveidah? What's
an example of an אבידה? avedah? מצא חמור או פרה רועים בדרך.
matza chamor o para ro'im baderech. Okay, that sounds like the פסוק.
Okay, כי תראה שור אויבך או חמורו נדחים. ki tir'eh shor oyvecha
o chamoro nidachim. איזו היא אבידה. eizo hi aveidah. That's not enough
to be a lost object, they're just grazing. Oh look, somebody's sheep
grazing, it's a lost object, I'll do a מצווה and return it.
No. חמור וכליו הפוכים פרה רצה בין הכרמים. chamor v'kelav hapuchim para
ratza bein hakramim. If you see a donkey and it's you know,
saddlebags are all turned upside down, or you see a cow that's
running among in the vineyards, הרי זו אבידה. harei zo aveidah. That
is not something a normal owner allows and that would be considered
an אבידה. avedah? החזירה וברחה החזירה וברחה, hechezira u'varcha hechezira u'varcha, אפילו
ארבע וחמש פעמים, afilu arba v'chamesh pe'amim, if you returned it and
it ran away, returned it and it ran away, so sometimes it's
an אבידה avedah not because it slipped out of the owner's pocket
but because it's a livestock and the animal escapes from its pen.
Okay, then חייב להחזירה, chayav l'hachzira, you must continue to return it
even if you've already returned it. שנאמר השב תשיבם, shene'emar hashev teshivem,
you shall surely return it, and the double language here means even
many many times, אפילו מאה פעמים. afilu me'ah pe'amim. היה בטל מסלע.
haya vatel misela. Now this is going back to something. Let's say
that to return this lost object would cost me a סלע Sela
of lost wages, $100 of lost wages. לא יאמר לו תן לי
סלע, Lo Yomar Lo Ten Li Sela, don't return the object and
say, "Okay, here's your lost object, but by the way, you know,
I lost out $100 from my job, so pay me $100." That
seems reasonable. No, says the משנה, Mishna, you're not allowed to say
that. אלא נותן לו שכרו כפועל, Ela Noten Lo Secharo KePoel, you
get paid as a worker. Now what that means is, okay, so
we will see. Anyway, what the גמרא Gemara is going to say
is, okay, jury duty, exactly, what a great example. So what the
גמרא Gemara is going to basically say is, okay, you didn't get
your $100 for your work, but then you would have had to
work harder to earn that $100. Here you got to just like
go enjoy the beautiful weather outdoors and go knocking door to door.
That was a lot easier job. So you're going to get paid,
but not be based on your other, on your normal wages. So
how exactly to figure out what you get reimbursed for, we'll see
in the גמרא, Gemara but it's not your normal wages. Okay. Now,
it could be that, it could be that actually my normal job
is easier than this, right? I'm a computer programmer, I love sitting
in front of my computer, I earn $100 an hour. This was
a much more of a pain in the neck, I had to
go outside, I had to interact with people, I had whatever, and
so it was more work and less remunerative, like it doesn't mean
that necessarily I prefer this. I actually would have preferred to be
working at my job, it actually would have been less work for
me and it would have paid more. So we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara But right now, it's basically saying don't assume
that you can get reimbursed for what your lost wages, because you
weren't working at your job. You were doing something other than your
job. So we'll see how you can get reimbursed in the גמרא
Gemara in one minute. אם יש שם בית דין, Im Yesh Sham
Beit Din, now let's say the reality is fine. I know based
on how the law is set up, as Jenna said, I'll get
jury, jury duty wages, I'll get, you know, $5 an hour or
something. I can't afford that. Okay? It might be even it makes
me work less, but you know what? I have a family to
feed. I can't afford just spending my time going door to door,
knocking on doors and doing whatever, posting things. I've got to go
work harder, go back to the stone quarry and earn $20 an
hour so I can feed my family. I can't take off time
to go ahead and do this. Okay? So that's true, אם יש
שם בית דין מתנה בפני בית דין, Im Yesh Sham Beit Din
Matne Bifnei Beit Din, you get a בית דין Beit Din together,
you get three people together and you say, "I'm returning this only
on the condition that the owner reimburses me based on the wages
I would have earned." And then you're allowed to do it. Right.
I know, well, we assume the owner will be okay up to
the value of the lost object, because it's better than him not
getting back his object altogether. אם אין שם בית דין בפני מי
יתנה, Im Ein Sham Beit Din Bifnei Mi Yatne, if there's not
a בית דין Beit Din to make this stipulation, and you cannot
lose these lost wages, so שלו קודם, Shelo Kodem, which is what
we saw before. I have to take care of my own sort
of financial well-being before somebody else's. Okay? My loss of money takes
precedence over your loss of money and I cannot lose these wages.
So if I have no way to protect these wages, I have
to go ahead and just forgo returning the object. Now it is
interesting, you know, the question that was asked before about like, well
why don't we just sort of say find somebody else who would
not lose out so much money and be happy to go return
and let that person turn and hand it off to that person.
Right? That idea of sort of seeing this as a responsibility to
see that it gets returned that would allow me to hand it
over is never expressed. It's always very focused on personal responsibility. Yes,
Jenna raises her hand so she gets precedence. Yes. You kind of
inserted that part about if I can't afford it, right, and I
need to feed my family? It's just, it's just a jump. It
just says if you want to. Right. So, yeah, that's a good
point. Meaning maybe I could afford it, but I'd rather get paid
a higher wage than a lower wage. It's a very good point.
I mean, I was reading רש"י Rashi into it. You're making a
second point, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, אם יש שם בית
דין אם נוח לו לטרוח יותר כדי להרבות שכר ואינו חפץ ליבטל
ממלאכתו מה יעשה. Im Yesh Sham Beit Din Im Noach Lo Litroach
Yoter Kedai Leharbot Sachar Ve'eino Chafetz Libatel Mimlachto Ma Ya'aseh. Right, I'd
rather do my work, my normal job, and get a higher pay.
Okay. But you're right. Let's say I actually would rather do this,
you know, I'm happy to do this and get $5 an hour
and take a little bit of a break from my work, but
heck, if I can get $20 an hour I'd rather get $20
an hour. So you're right, it's not explicit. But רש"י Rashi sort
of says, you know, maybe that's what the בית דין Beit Din
would have to agree to, like you know, but you're right, רש"י
Rashi reads into it that it has to be that this is
a sort of a, it's not like I would refuse to do
it otherwise, but at least that all things being equal I would
rather just keep on doing my job. You know, there needs to
be something justifying. Could it be like you're going to starve that
night? Right, right, right. I was trying to give a colorful example.
But you're right, the משנה Mishna doesn't give any criteria. According to
the משנה Mishna maybe I just want to earn a higher wage
rather than a lower wage. But at least רש"י Rashi says there
has to be some justification why we're going to agree to let
you get this higher wage. Yes. And you're also reading, you know,
or the גמרא Gemara is reading into this earlier, and that the
value of the object exceeds, you know, the, the wages that you
pay. I mean, no, that's not about the value exceeding. This is
just that you don't want, you can't stand, you can't deal with
the loss. Oh, I mean, no, there's a third case, which is
that even if there is a בית דין... Beit Din... It won't
work to deal with a בית דין. Beis Din. That's a different
case, not in the משנה. Mishnah. Right, there's one case that because
of the בית דין Beis Din I'll return it but because the
owner will agree to pay me my higher wage because in the
end he'll get more, he'll come up with the net gain. If
he pay my higher wage would mean that the owner would actually
get a net loss, then that's the earlier גמרא. Gemara Then I
just move on. Right. Correct. I think it is, you know, some
some אומדנות, umdenos, like, you know, all right, let's say a new
one is $100, or the old one will be $90. I'd rather
just get a new one already. Yeah, I know. Right. You have
to figure that out. Okay, maybe that's part of what the בית
דין Beis Din does. Let's take a look in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay, אטו כל הני דאמינן לאו אבידה הוי? atu kol hanei d'aminan
lav avedah havei? What do you mean what's an אבידה? avedah. An
animal this way as opposed to that way. We've been talking about
it since the beginning of the פרק. perek. So obviously, but part
of the point is that now we're dealing more closely with sort
of articulating the הלכה halakhah based on the פסוקים. psukim. So since
the פסוקים psukim talk about a wandering animal or whatever, so that's
why the משנה Mishnah does. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara
responds. It's a funny way to introduce it. What's an אבידה? avedah,
אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר: amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar: איזו היא
כלל אבידה שהוא חייב בה? Eizu hi klal avedah shehu chayav bah?
What is like a, as רש"י Rashi says, like a type of
an אבידה avedah that's obvious that it's a lost object? מצא חמור
או פרה רועין בדרך, matza chamor o parah ro'in baderech, אין זו
אבידה, ein zo avedah, ולא מיחייב בה. v'lo michayav bah. If they're
just grazing, that's not a lost object. חמור וכליו הפוכין פרה רצה
בין הכרמים הרי זו אבידה ומיחייב בה. chamor v'cheilav hafuchin parah ratzah
bein hakramim harei zo avedah u'michayav bah. Okay, but if it's sort
of clearly the saddlebags are overturned, or it's whatever, running through the
vineyard, then clearly it's an אבידה. avedah. So the way רש"י Rashi
reads it, it depends on like what makes it a clear אבידה,
avedah. but it's also I think what's like the אבידה avedah. of
the פסוקים psukim is probably more what the משנה Mishnah is saying.
Okay, ולעולם? u'l'olam? So now the גמרא Gemara says if, right, that's
a question, right? So now if it says if it was grazing
by the, it was grazing on the way, you don't have to
return it. Really? Even if it's been grazing there for the last
month? Like, you know, it's clear that like, if an owner would
have been taken in at night or something like that. So sometimes
even if it looks like it's normal, you know, it's like if
you see a dog walking around the street, right, in a suburban
area, so, you know, you don't assume it's an אבידה. avedah. But
if you keep on seeing it and you never see an owner
around or whatever, at a certain point you wonder, like, it looks
like it must be a lost dog, yeah? Like for two weeks
if it's still there, right? It's about, it's about like how long
do you watch this thing? Exactly. So that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
After a certain point, you do assume it's an אבידה. avedah. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב: amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: עד שלושה ימים.
ad shlosha yamim. Three days. After three days and there's no owner
to be seen, you assume it's an אבידה. avedah So the גמרא
Gemara says: היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי בליליותא, iy
b'leilyusa, if it's out grazing at night, אפילו חדא שעתא נמי, afilu
chada sha'atah nami, even one hour, owners don't let their animals graze
at night, that should be enough evidence. אי ביממא, iy b'yimama, if
you see it's three days in the daytime, day after day, אפילו
טובא נמי לא. afilu tuva nami lo. So the owner is not
there during the day, but he'll come at night and he'll retrieve
it. So it could be many days and you don't see the
owner around. So the גמרא says no, לא צריכא דהוי חזי ליה
בקדמותא ובחשכתא. lo tzricha d'havei chazi lei b'kadmusa u'v'chashachta. You are an
early riser, you would see it an hour before dawn out there
grazing, and you would see it an hour into night grazing. Okay,
is it possible that the owner let it out to graze very
early and was very late in taking it back? Yes. Okay, but
it's more likely that the reason you saw it early before dawn
and a first hour into night is because the owner is not
retrieving it and there's no owner around. Okay, עד תלתא יומי, ad
tlosha yomei, if this goes on for three days, אמרינן אשתרומי אשתרומי
ליה, amrinan ishtrumay ishtrumay lei, up to three days. ונפק v'nafak טפי.
tfei. Up to three days we say, "Yeah, that's just what happened.
The owner sort of let it out for more time, let it
out early, took it in late." Okay, ונפק v'nafak טפי, tfei, more
than three days, ודאי אבידה היא. vaday avedah hi. No, then the
evidence is showing that there is no owner around and it's been
out there grazing all night and then you have to go ahead
and take it in. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught
similarly: מצא טלית וקרדום באסרטיא, matza tallis v'kardom b'istratya, if you found
a טלית tallis or a hammer in like the middle of the
main street, ופרה רצה בין הכרמים, u'parah ratzah bein hakramim, or a
cow running between the vineyards. You see a cow run? I know.
הרי זו אבידה. harei zo avedah. That's an אבידה. aveidah, טלית בצד
גדר, tallis b'tzad geder, קרדום בצד גדר, kardom b'tzad geder, if you
found a טלית tallis by a wall or a hammer by a
wall, ופרה רועה בין הכרמים, u'parah ro'ah bein hakramim, or a cow
just grazing in the vineyards or some have the גירסא girsah בין
הצבים bein hatzavim in the clouds, we'll see about that in a
minute. אין זו אבידה. ein zo avedah. That's not an אבידה. aveidah?
ג' ימים זה אחר זה, gimmel yamim zeh achar zeh, but if
it goes on for three days, הרי זו אבידה, harei zo avedah,
which is what we were discussing before. ראה מים ששוטפין ובאין, ra'ah
mayim sheshofin u'ba'in, הרי זה גודר בפניהם. harei zeh goder bifneihem. If
you saw water which was coming to flood somebody's field, you have
an obligation to, you know, build a fence, build a wall to
stop the water. Okay, it's like, you know, like a, right, when
a river's about to overflow and all the town gets together to
like build up the, you know, retaining wall or whatever. Oh, it
might have to be your existing gate, right? I mean... Well, it
depends, depends on no, what do you mean? ראה מים ששוטפין, ra'ah
mayim sheshofin, ששוטפין sheshofin might be it's a heavy rain and you
see the river's going to overflow and everybody gets together to build
sandbags. Okay, could be. אמר רבא: Rava Now, this is an important
idea because for two reasons. It conceptualizes it, abstracts אבידה aveidah in
two ways. The גמרא's going to have to... abstracts it to apply
to land. Normally you talk about an object that you pick up
an object and you look for the owner. Here the owner is
here, the owner has his object, but you still have to protect
it even though it's not an object, even though it's the land.
But more than that I would say for me what's more interesting
is, is that it's protecting somebody against a loss rather than returning
somebody's object to them. And the idea that the mitzvah of השבת
אבידה hashavat aveidah obligates me to protect you from a loss that
you're about to incur. Okay, now what exactly does that mean? I
don't know, like if I hear, I don't know, you know, I
hear that some business deal going on, we'll assume it's not insider
trading and I know that you're invested in this company, you know,
and I know that you whatever, do I have an obligation now
to call up everybody who I know is invested in the company
so they don't suffer as a result of their, I mean, what
exactly is the urgency and the immediacy of the law? Are we
talking about physical loss? Here the actual property is going to be
injured as opposed to just, you know, like loss of investment. So
it's an interesting question once you abstract this. Okay, but the our
idea that the mitzvah of השבת אבידה hashavat aveidah includes protection against
loss and not just returning an object is a very important one.
So אמר רבא לכל אבידת אחיך Amar Rava lekhol aveidat achikha לרבות
אבידת קרקע lerabbot aveidat karka to include even if it's land that
is going to be damaged. אמר ליה רב חנינא לרבא Amar lei
Rav Chanina le-Rava or רב חנניה, Rav Chananya, excuse me, said to
רבא, Rava תניא דמסייע לך tanya demisayye’a lakh I have a braita
that supports you, exactly this braita. ראשי מים ששוטפין ובאין rashei mayim
she-shotfin u-va’in הרי זה גודר בפניהם. harei zeh goder bifneihem. So that's
like your point that you have to protect even land against a
loss. אמר ליה Amar lei. no, אם משום הא לא תסייע. im
mishum ha lo tessayye’. That is not sufficient to support me. הכא
במאי עסקינן hakha be-mai askinan I could say that the case there
is בדיקא ועומרין be-dika ve-omerin that when it means that you have
to build a wall to protect the field from being flooded, it's
not to protect the field, it's to protect the bundles of wheat
in the field. That's what you're protecting and it's still an idea
of a מצוות השבת אבידה mitzvot hashavat aveidah by an object and
not by land. Okay, אי דאיכא עומרין i de-ika omerin the Gemara
says מאי למימרא mai le-meimra then isn't that obvious? Again, I would
say it's not obvious because the thing is not lost, it's just
about to be lost. You know, there's definitely a חידוש chidush there.
But the Gemara says no, לא צריכא דאית בה עומרין דצריכי לארעא
lo tzerikha de-it beh omerin de-tzrikhei le-ar’a that the bundles are still
sort of needed for the land. I don't know why they need
the land, but okay, whatever. מהו דתימא mahu de-teima כיון דצריכי לארעא
keivan de-tzrikhei le-ar’a כגופא דארעא דמי ke-gufa de-ar’a dami maybe I would
think it becomes like part of the landscape and then there isn't
a מצוות השבת mitzvot hashavat קמשמע לן ka mashma lan that there
is. So the גמרא here questions whether it applies to land as
we've seen until before now like by גניבה וגזילת קרקע gneivah u-gezeilat
karka that there's a formal way of excluding land from some of
these obligations. And the Torah talks about returning an object, something that
can get moved and separated from the owner. So that's like one
level. So right, if the you know, if the bundle of wheat
will get destroyed, it's sort of more similar to me dropping my
bundle of wheat in the רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim and never getting
it back. It's I've been separated from it, I've lost it and
so on. Will you also explain it, extend it to the idea
of my land being destroyed? And that's the Gemara leaves as an
open-ended question. But what either way you see is that if we
are at least talking about a concrete object, protecting against it being
destroyed is part of the מצוות השבת mitzvot hashavat not just returning
it when it is physically lost. And that becomes important also in
the following scenario, where do you get the idea that there is
a מצוה mitzvah of פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, a mitzvah of taking
care of somebody whose life or you know or health is at
risk? Okay, where does that mitzvah come from? Some people say לא
תעמוד על דם רעך, lo ta’amod al dam re’akha, but that's like
a לא תעשה. lo ta’aseh. That's not a like a mandate to
positive mandate to do something for someone. So one of the sources
is the idea of השבת אבידה. hashavat aveidah. Okay, which is now
how does that get to השבת אבידה? hashavat aveidah? Well, if השבת
אבידה hashavat aveidah means protecting your property against loss, not just returning
it, but protecting it against loss, then also it would be protecting
you against injury. So if I have a mitzvah to protect your
property that's about to be injured, I have a mitzvah to protect
you if you are going to, right, קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. So
it's a very important broad sort of, you know, sort of interpersonal
mandate obligation that's not just now about lost objects. Okay, it's really
about protecting people and their property. Alright,
so now the Gemara goes on, begin just before, you can still
charge for that, you know, yeah, yeah, right. מצא חמור ופרה. matza
chamor u-farah. So now we now we deal with the donkey and
the cow. So the Gemara says הגופא קשיא, ha gufa kashya,
this is an internal contradiction. אמרת amarta מצא חמור ופרה רועין בדרך
matza chamor u-farah ro’in ba-derekh grazing on the way, אין זו אבידה.
ein zo aveidah. רועין בדרך הוא דלא הויא אבידה. ro’in ba-derekh hu
de-la havya aveidah. So there are two good criteria that indicate it's
not lost. Number one, it's grazing, it's not running. Okay, and number
two, it's grazing
in a normal place, it's grazing on the way, which is on
the on the path I guess, which is a normal place. הא
רצה בדרך ורועה בין הכרמים ha ratzah ba-derekh ve-ro’ah bein ha-kramim if
you were missing either one of those criteria, it was running even
on a path, or if it was grazing in a vineyard, הויא
אבידה havya aveidah that would be an aveidah because you don't have
both criteria. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end. חמור
וכלים הפוכין ופרה רצה בין הכרמים chamor ve-kelim hafukhin u-farah ratzah bein
ha-kramim a cow running in the vineyard, הרי זו אבידה. harei zo
aveidah. That is an aveidah. That has both negative criteria, running and
in the vineyard. רצה בין ratzah bein Running in the vineyard is
an אבידה aveidah, *aveidah*. If it had only one of the criteria,
running, but it was running on a path, or רועה בין הכרמים
*ro'eh bein hakramim*, or grazing in the vineyards, אין זו אבידה aveidah
*ein zo aveidah*, it would not be. So what is it? Do
you need both criteria for it to be an אבידה *aveidah*? Or
both negative criteria for it not to be an אבידה *aveidah*? Or
I mean both negative criteria for it to be an אבידה *aveidah*?
So אמר אביי *Amar Abaye* said אביי *Abaye*, יגיד עליו רעו *yagid
alav re'o*, let its friend tell about it, meaning let's figure it
out, you know, let the context define what we mean. תנא *Tanna*,
רועה בדרך דלא הוי אבידה *ro'eh baderech delo havi aveidah*, the משנה
Mishna. *Mishnah* says that if it's grazing on the path, it's not
an אבידה *aveidah*. So since we're talking about grazing, it would really
mean all types of grazing, even grazing in the vineyards, because we're
going to mention vineyards later, so grazing here in the path includes
grazing in the vineyards. Now when it says תנא רצה בין הכרמים
דהוי אבידה *Tanna ratzah bein hakramim dehavi aveidah*, running in the vineyards
is an אבידה *aveidah*, so we also mentioned path earlier, so it's
not really about path versus vineyards. It's about grazing versus running. הוא
הדין לרצה בדרך *Hu hadin leratzah baderech*, running even on a path
would be it. So because one thing talks about the path and
one talk about vineyards, they're both talking about paths and vineyards. That's
not the difference. The difference is running versus grazing. אמר ליה Amar
lei. רבא Rava *Amar leih Rava*, יגיד עליו רעו *yagid alav re'o*,
if you want to learn it out from context, ליתני קילתא וכל
שכן חמירתא *lisni kilta vekholsheken chamirta*. It should have taught the more
lenient and I could have figured out the more stringent, meaning it
still tell me the bigger חידוש Chiddush? *chiddush* is basically what רבא
Rava *Rava* is saying. You don't have to say path and vineyards
in both cases. I can get that one case you say path,
one case you say vineyards, and you really mean either for both.
But tell it in a way that makes the bigger חידוש Chiddush.
*chiddush*. ליתני רצה בדרך דהוי אבידה *Lisni ratzah baderech dehavi aveidah*, say
running on a path is an אבידה *aveidah*, וכל שכן רצה בין
הכרמים *vekholsheken ratzah bein hakramim*, and certainly I'll figure out, oh, if
running on a path is an אבידה *aveidah*, certainly running in a
vineyard. וליתני רועה בין הכרמים דלא הוי אבידה *Velisni ro'eh bein hakramim
delo havi aveidah*, and say grazing in the vineyard is not an
אבידה *aveidah*, וכל שכן רועה בדרך *vekholsheken ro'eh baderech*, and certainly grazing
on the path. So I can get you don't have to say
the word path and vineyard in both cases, but do it in
the way that doesn't leave there to be an ambiguity about these
middle types of scenarios. אלא אמר רבא *Ella amar Rava*, so rather
רבא *Rava* says, רצה ארצה לא קשיא *ratza aratza lo kashya*. What
seems to be a contradiction of the implications of the two scenarios
of running is not a problem. You're right, one suggests running in
a path is an אבידה *aveidah*, one suggests it's not. So he
says it depends on context. הא דאפא לגבי דברא הא דאפא לגבי
מתא *Ha de'appa legabei dabra ha de'appa legabei mata*. Which way is
it running? If it's running out away from the city and it's
on the path, that's an אבידה *aveidah*. If it's running into the
city, it's not an אבידה *aveidah*. That's like that old Chassidic story
that Rabbi Weiss loves to tell. The Rebbe asks his students, he
says, you know on the ladder, the fifty rungs up to heaven,
right, who's higher, the guy who's on, you know, the fortieth rung
or the guy who's on the tenth rung? And the חסידים *Chassidim*
say the guy's on the fortieth rung. And the Rebbe says, no,
depends which direction they're going. So there you go, depends which way
the animal's running. Okay, so רועה ארועה נמי לא קשיא *ro'eh aro'eh
nami lo kashya*. How about whether it's grazing in the vineyards, is
that an אבידה *aveidah*? So he says it's not a problem, sometimes
yes, sometimes no. כאן באבידת גופא כאן באבידת קרקע *Kan be'aveidat gufa
kan be'aveidat karka*. Regarding the animal itself, grazing in the vineyards is
not an אבידה *aveidah*. Okay, I the owner might have like have
left the animal graze in the vineyards, okay, but you know what
is an אבידה *aveidah*? The land, the vineyards. Okay, you've got to
take, you've got to do something about it to protect the vineyards.
So גמרא *Gemara* says, כאן באבידת קרקע *kan be'aveidat karka*. כי תני
רועה בדרך לא הוי אבידה הא רועה בין הכרמים הוי אבידה *Ki
tana ro'eh baderech lo havi aveidah ha ro'eh bein hakramim havi aveidah*.
The implication that only grazing in the way is not a problem,
is not an אבידה *aveidah*, but grazing in the vineyards is? אבידת
קרקע *aveidat karka*. That means that that's not a tolerable situation because
the vineyards are being destroyed. ואי תני רצה בין הכרמים הוי אבידה
הא רועה בין הכרמים לא הוי אבידה *Ve'i tana ratzah bein hakramim
havi aveidah ha ro'eh bein hakramim lo havi aveidah*. When it says
running in the vineyards is an אבידה *aveidah*, grazing is not, that
means באבידת גופא *be'aveidat gufa*. That means the animal is not an
אבידה *aveidah*.
דרצה בין הכרמים *Deratzah bein hakramim*. Now why is it that if
it's grazing in the vineyards, I should assume the animal is not
lost? דרצה בין הכרמים *Deratzah bein
hakramim*, because an owner would never let his animal run through the
vineyards. Why? Because running through the vineyards מסקיבא *miskiva*, the animal would
get injured by the thorns and by the, you know, whatever of
the vineyard. So therefore the owner would never let his animal run
through the vineyards, it's clearly an אבידה *aveidah*. ורועה בין הכרמים לא
מסקיבא *Vero'eh bein hakramim lo miskiva*. But grazing the animal won't be
injured, so the owner might have might be allowing it, maybe he
doesn't care about somebody else's property, but you still have to intervene
to protect somebody else's property. So גמרא *Gemara* says, ורועה בין הכרמים
אי דלא מסקיבא תיפוק ליה משום אבידת קרקע *Vero'eh bein hakramim i
delo miskiva teipokei leih mishum aveidat karka*. Okay, says גמרא *Gemara*,
but how could the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* imply that you could be
cool with that's a technical halakhic term, cool with the idea that
the animal is grazing in a vineyard, if you just got through
telling me that there's אבידת קרקע *aveidat karka*? Still going to be
a problem of protecting the vineyard? So the גמרא says בדוכתי. B'duchti.
What's בדוכתי? B'duchti? Hold on. בדוקותי! B'dukoti! Oh, no wonder, I was
reversing the ו Vav and the כ. Chaf. And it shouldn't be
בדוקותי B'dukoti anyway, I'm sure somebody has the שטינזלץ, Steinsaltz, it's
probably בדנוכרי, B'denochri, right? Okay, anyway. So the point is is that
you're in a... the vineyard is not owned
by a Jew. So as we've seen before, you
don't have to, according to the
strict הלכה, Halacha, although there could be a לפנים משורת הדין Lifnim
Mishurat Hadin here as well, but according to the strict הלכה, Halacha,
you're not obligated if it's not the property... if the property does
not belong to a Jew. So it's the animal of a Jew
but not the vineyard of a Jew. ותיפוק ליה משום אבידת גופא
דלמא קטלו לה. V'teipok lei mishum aveidat gufa dilma katlu lah. Okay,
but the גמרא says if that's true, you anyway forget the idea
of the vineyard, it should still be a concern about protecting the
animal because if the animal is grazing in somebody else's vineyard, the
owners are going to shoot the animal, right? You got like these
wild deer that go around and they whatever, they graze in people's
fields and then they get shot. So shouldn't you be obligated to
protect the animal if it's in somebody else's vineyard even if the...
you know, regardless of the vineyard? So the גמרא says באתרא דמסרו
והדר קטלו. B'asra de'masru vehadar katlu. No, no, it's a place where
they have to first give warning before they shoot the animal. Okay,
warning to the owners presumably. So the גמרא says ודלמא אסרו בה?
V'dilma asru bah? So maybe they've already given warning to the owners
and this is the second time, so maybe you have to protect
the animal in this case? אי אסרו בה ולא איזדהרו בה הרי
אבדה מדעתו. Ee asru bah velo izdharu bah harei aveida mida'ata. If
the owners have been warned and they weren't careful and let their
animal go out and graze again into somebody else's vineyard, then you
get what's coming to you. Okay, then you are willing to allow
it to be killed and you brought it... so it's not really
considered an אבדה Aveida that you have an obligation to, it's the
type of thing that implicitly the owner has sort of accepted the
risk. Okay, but I mean the first time, then you should give
it back so it won't get to a point where he needs
to be warned? No, that's not a real... that's not direct damage
to the... danger. That's just, you know, causing somebody higher risk in
the future. Okay. השב תשיבם. Hashev teshivem. If you turned it and
it ran away, you have to keep on returning it. You don't
get exempt just because you did it once. אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן
לרבא. Amar lei hahu me'rabanan le'Rava. So one of the רבנן Rabanan
said to רבא, אימא השב חדא זימנא תשיבם תרי זימני. Eima Hashev
chada zimna teshivem try zimnei. How does השב תשיבם Hashev teshivem mean
even a hundred times? Maybe השב תשיבם Hashev teshivem means twice. Okay,
it says it twice. Okay. אמר ליה. So now what רבא's going
to respond is the...
is not the פשט Pshat of the משנה. The פשט Pshat of
the משנה makes it sound that the
doubling of the word means... means a hundred times, and רבא's going
to say it's not the doubling that means a hundred times, even
the first word means a hundred times. השב אפילו מאה פעמים משמע.
Hashev afilu me'ah pe'amim mashma. השב Hashev means even a hundred times
without תשיבם. Teshivem. Now, it's too bad that Rabbi Dover's not here,
I don't know if anybody here knows grammar. I don't, but I
think the point is it's the use of the word השב Hashev
versus the word you'd use תשיב. Tashiv. No, right. תשיב Tashiv means
you shall return it. השב Hashev i think is more ongoing. השב
Hashev is like it shall be returned. Okay, so because it's this
more ongoing sense, it means no matter how many times. Yeah, yeah,
from what... from what you know of grammar, that's correct? I think
so. Anyway, I think that's רבא's point. השב אפילו מאה פעמים משמע.
Hashev afilu me'ah pe'amim mashma. תשיבם, Teshivem, so then what do you
do with תשיבם? Teshivem? אין לי אלא לביתו, גנתו וחורבתו מנין? תלמוד
לומר תשיבם מכל מקום. Ein li ela leveito, ginato ucharto minayin? Talmud
lomar teshivem mikol makom. I only know that it's... that it's only
good enough if you put it straight into the guy's house. How
do I know you can just return it to his garden or
his yard? תלמוד לומר תשיבם מכל מקום. Talmud lomar teshivem mikol makom.
That broadens it; other forms of return also work. So now the
גמרא says right, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's a case? אי דמינטרא,
Ee demintara, if you're returning it to a place that's protected and
guarded, you know, a fenced-in area, פשיטא, Pshita, of course. What difference
does it make, the house or the yard? אי דלא מינטרא, Ee
de'la mintara, and if it's not guarded or protected, אמאי? Amai? Why
would that be a good return? לעולם דמינטרא. Le'olam demintara. Yes, it
is protected. So what's the חידוש? מהו דתימא בעינן דעת בעלים. Mahu
de'teima ba'inan da'at ba'alim. which says a big חידוש. You don't have
to knock on the guy's house and say I'm returning your sheep.
You can just put
the sheep back in the pen. You found the owner, you went
back to his... he's not around, just put it back in the
pen and go home. Okay. כדרבי אלעזר, K'de'Rabbi Elazar, like Rabbi Elazar
says. דאמר הכל צריכין דעת בעלים חוץ מהשבת אבידה שהתורה ריבתה השבות
הרבה. De'amar hakol tzrichin da'at ba'alim chutz me'hashevat aveida she'hatorah ribta hashavot
harbeh. any type of paying back somebody, you have to inform the
person you're paying back, or let's say גניבה וגזילה, geneiva u'gezeila, you're
returning the stolen thing, חוץ מהשבת אבידה, chutz me'hashevat aveida, except for
returning a lost object, because the תורה Torah ריבתה השבות הרבה, ribta
hashavot harbeh, which means many forms of return, even if they don't
know. And we have to move on. שלח תשלח. Shale'ach tishalach. So
we're going to deal with a lot of double languages. Okay. שלח
תשלח את האם, Shale'ach tishalach et ha'em, by sending away the mother
bird. And in חולין Chulin we say that means even if it
comes back, you have to do it a hundred times. Same idea,
of doing it a hundred times. So the גמרא says אימא שלח
חדא זימנא תשלח תרי זימני. Eima Shale'ach chada zimna tishalach try zimnei.
Maybe here it also only means twice. How do you learn out
a hundred times? אמר ליה. So רבא responded again, this is... רבא
responding to one of the רבנן. Rabanan. No. שלח, Shale'ach, the ongoing
sense of שלח, Shale'ach, אפילו מאה פעמים משמע. afilu me'ah pe'amim mashma.
Just from the word שלח, Shale'ach, we know you have to do
it a hundred times. תשלח, Tishalach, what does that mean? אין לי
אלא לדבר הרשות. Ein li ela lidvar hareshut. I only know you
have to do the מצוה Mitzvah of שלוח Shiluach of sending away
the mother bird if you're taking the chicks for a... for a
sort of a neutral purpose, like you know you just... just want
to eat them. לדבר מצוה מנין, lidvar mitzvah minayin, let's say you're
taking them a bird to do the mitzvah of like of a
by the מצורע, metzora, of the קרבן, korban, of right, of טהרת
מצורע. taharat metzora. Do I know that the mitzvah of sending away
the mother bird applies there as well? תלמוד לומר תשלח מכל מקום,
talmud lomar tishalach mikol makom, the double language tells you even in
a broader scenario. So the idea of many times this is going
to be the pattern is learned out from the first word. The
doubling expands the number of cases to which it applies. Okay, אמרי
ליה רבנן לרבא. amrei lei rabbanan le-Rava. So one of the rabbis
said to Rava, ואימא הוכח חד זימנא תוכיח תרי זימני. ve'eima hocheach
chad zimna tochiach trei zimnei. How do you know you have to
do הוכחה hochacha 100 times, you know, keep on giving somebody מוסר
mussar to try to change their act? And of course there is
a limit if you know if he embarrasses you if you embarrass
whatever there's limits to it, okay, but but nevertheless the idea is
you have to do it ongoing so how do you know maybe
it's also only twice? הוכח תוכיח hocheach tochiach maybe that only means
twice? אמר ליה הוכח אפילו מאה פעמים משמע. amar lei hocheach afilu
me'ah pe'amim mashma. No, the word הוכח hocheach by itself means ongoing.
תוכיח, tochiach, what does תוכיח tochiach come to tell me? אין לי
אלא רב לתלמיד. ein li ela rav letalmid. I only know that
a master has to give, you know, remonstrate his student. תלמיד לרב
מנין? talmid lerav minayin? How do I know that it would even
go against like the normal you know respect? I mean you have
to do it in a respectful way but even somebody who is
a disciple is allowed to do it to a master, or is
obligated to do it to a master? תלמוד לומר הוכח תוכיח מכל
מקום talmud lomar hocheach tochiach mikol makom in even a broad range
of cases. עזוב תעזוב עמו, azov ta'azov imo, this is about the
loading up the guy's donkey after you helped unload it. So אין
לי אלא בעליו עמו. ein li ela be'alav imo. I only know
you're obligated if the owner is willing to help you. שאין בעליו
עמו מנין? she'ein be'alav imo minayin? How do I know even if
the owner is not or is not around that you have to
do it even if it's not תעזוב עמו? ta'azov imo? Because the
word says עזוב תעזוב עמו. azov ta'azov imo. Let's say the owner
is not around or is not going to help you because it's
beneath his dignity like we saw before. How do I know even
then you're obligated to load up the donkey? תלמוד לומר עזוב תעזוב,
talmud lomar azov ta'azov, you should surely help him, okay, מכל מקום.
mikol makom. Now you still have to do it? You do have
to. Okay actually I misspoke עזוב תעזוב azov ta'azov is actually the
unloading. It's a little ambiguous like the Gemara is going to say
in a minute. So yes now if he refuses to help you
he's there and he's capable and he refuses you don't have to
but if he's not around or it's beneath his dignity or he's
not able to help you you still have to. So the double
language one word tells you מאה פעמים me'ah pe'amim and the double
language tells you even if he's not able to help you, even
if it's not עמו. imo. That's unloading. הקם תקים, hakem takim, this
is reloading the animal עמו. imo. Now again the verse says עמו
imo with him. אין לי אלא בעליו עמו. ein li ela be'alav
imo. שאין בעליו עמו מנין? she'ein be'alav imo minayin? תלמוד לומר הקם
תקים מכל מקום. talmud lomar hakem takim mikol makom. Okay even if
he's not able to help or he's not around you have to
do it. So הקם hakem itself tells you מאה פעמים, me'ah pe'amim,
the double language tells you even if the owner is not there.
Okay ולמה לי למכתב פריקה ולמה לי למכתב טעינה? velamma lei lemichtav
prika velamma lei lemichtav te'ina? Why did the Torah have to both
tell me unload and load? You know just tell me basically load
back up and certainly I would have to unload because the animal
is suffering. Okay צריכי. tzrichi. No you need both. דאי כתב רחמנא
פריקה חדא הוה אמינא משום צער בעלי חיים. de'i katav rachmana prika
hada havel amina mishum tza'ar ba'alei chayim. Had it just said unload
an animal I would have thought it's because of צער בעלי חיים,
tza'ar ba'alei chayim, there's a couple of reasons to unload an animal,
the animal is suffering, ואיכא חסרון כיס ve'ika chissaron kis and the
owner is losing out, the animal might die or his wares aren't
getting to the city. So that's obvious you're obligated. אבל טעינה דלאו
צער בעלי חיים איכא ולאו חסרון כיס איכא aval te'ina d'lav tza'ar
ba'alei chayim ika velav chissaron kis ika but loading up the animal
where a the animal is not suffering if you don't load it
up b the loss is not as obvious the animal is not
going to die and maybe he'll get somebody else to help him
to bring the stuff to the city so אימא לא eima lo
maybe you don't have to help him so that's obviously why you
have to talk about the obligation of reloading it you can't infer
it from the obligation of unloading. ואשמעינן טעינה ve'ishmi'enan te'ina if you
talk to me just the obligation of loading משום דבשכר mishum deschar
because we're going to learn out that you're actually allowed to get
paid for helping him reload the animal but not to unload. Okay
unload is like השבת אבידה, hashavat aveidah, it's protecting against a loss,
reload is like you're like a worker you're helping him do his
work okay so then I would know fine loading you can you
have to do because you can get paid for it אבל פריקה
דבחינם aval prika d'bechinam but I might not have been able to
infer from that that I have an obligation to unload for free
just because the Torah told me I have an obligation to load
and to be paid for it. אימא לא eima lo maybe I
would not have known it צריכי tzrichi you need both. ולרבי שמעון
דאמר אף טעינה בחינם ule-Rabbi Shimon d'amar af te'ina bechinam and for
Rabbi Shimon that says you even have to load it up for
free מאי איכא למימר mai ika lemeimar why not just say a
mitzvah to load and I can infer a mitzvah to unload? So
the Gemara says רבי שמעון לא מסיימי קרא. Rabbi Shimon lo mesaymi
kera. No because the פסוקים pesukim as I just made a mistake
unintentionally earlier הקם תקים hakem takim and עזוב תעזוב azov ta'azov are
not so clear whether they're talking about unloading or loading so I
only would have known both an obligation to load and unload if
it says it twice. If it would have said only one I
would have read it as an obligation to unload. It was not
necessarily clear enough from the verb whether it's referring to loading or
unloading. Okay let's just do one more. למה לי למכתב הני תרתי
ולמה לי למכתב אבידה? lamma lei lemichtav hani tarti velamma lei lemichtav
aveidah? There's a very important conceptual idea. Why does the Torah have
to both say a mitzvah of unload and a mitzvah of returning
a lost object? Aren't they all the same idea protecting somebody's property,
especially a minute ago we just abstracted the idea of אבידה, protecting
property against loss. So why do we need it both in the
case of unloading and the case of אבידה? So גמרא says צריכי,
tzrichi, you need both. דאי כתב רחמנא הני תרתי, dei katav rachmana
hani tarti, if it had just had the loading, unloading, משום דצערא
דמרי איתא צערא דדידה איתא, mishum detza'ara demarei ita tza'ara dedidah ita,
because there you have both the anguish of the owner and the
anguish of the object itself, of the animal, okay? Unloading. Well I
know, means just a package. Okay. אבל אבידה דצערא דמרי איתא, aval
aveidah detza'ara demarei ita, but אבידה which is the anguish of the
owner because he lost his object, צערא דדידה ליתא, tza'ara dedidah leita,
the animal's now roaming free, maybe, and there's no צער בעלי חיים
tzar ba'alei chayim there, okay? So that case אימא לא, eima lo,
I might think you don't have an obligation. It might even have
been about צער בעלי חיים, tzar ba'alei chayim, okay? But ואי אשמעינן
אבידה, ve'ei ashmeinan aveidah, if it had told me אבידה, משום דליתא
למרה בהדה, mishum deleita lemarei bahadah, because there it's much more of
a loss to the owner, the owner's not around. If I don't
help, the guy's money's going to be lost. אבל הני תרתי דאיתא
למרה בהדה, aval hani tarti deita lemarei bahadah, but unloading, loading, where
the owner is there, I could say, hey buddy, you're there, you
take care of your own object. אימא לא, eima lo, צריכה. tzricha.
So one tells me that one is a case of צער בעלי
חיים, tzar ba'alei chayim, and so and I shouldn't limit it to
צער בעלי חיים, tzar ba'alei chayim, I have to understand that there's
a general מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה, hashavat aveidah, okay? But in
but also there's one case where the owner is there, and I
have to learn that even if the owner is there, like you
know, I have an obligation. And that could be even in an
אבידה case, like let's say the case about the thing that's about
to flood. The owner is there. I can't say, why don't you
just go get on the phone and call the dam building service
and let them do it. No, even if the owner is there,
I'm here too, and he needs me to help him. That's part
of my מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה. hashavat aveidah. So it applies
even without צער בעלי חיים tzar ba'alei chayim and even if the
owner is present. Okay, we will continue tomorrow.